It might be hard to believe, but traces of supernova explosions that occurred millions of years ago are imprinted in Earth's deep ocean floor.
信じられないかもしれませんが地球の深海には数百万年前に起きた超新星爆発の痕跡が刻まれているんです
It's hard to believe at first that evidence of stellar explosions in space has been left at the bottom of the ocean.
宇宙で起きた星の爆発の証拠が海の底に残されていたなんてにわかには信じがたいですよね
The key to solving this mystery is a special and extremely rare substance called iron-60.
その謎を解き明かす鍵となるのが鉄60という特殊で激レアな物質
Today, let's explore how this special iron,
今日はこの普通の鉄とは異なる特別な鉄が
which differs from ordinary iron,
どうやって壮大な宇宙の歴史を語ってくれるのか
tells us the grand history of the universe.
一緒に探っていきましょう
First, let me explain about our main character, iron-60.
まず主役の鉄60について説明します
The iron you're familiar with is iron-56.
皆さんがよく知っている鉄は鉄56
It has 26 protons and 30 neutrons in its nucleus.
原子核に陽子26個と中性子30個を持っています
But iron-60, which we're discussing today, is a special type of iron with as many as 34 neutrons.
でも今日お話しする鉄60は中性子が34個もあるちょっと特殊な鉄なんです
Iron-60 is actually radioactive and slowly transforms into another element over an incredibly long period of 2.6 million years.
この鉄60実は放射性物質で260万年という気の遠くなるような時間をかけてゆっくりと別の元素に変わっていきます
2.6 million years is roughly the same time from when our stone-tool-using ancestors appeared to the present day.
260万年って石器を使う人類の祖先が誕生してから現在までの時間とほぼ同じ
That's how long it is.
それくらい長い時間です
But here's an important point.
でもここで重要なポイントがあります
Iron-60 is not naturally produced on Earth.
鉄60は地球上では自然に作られないんです
So where did it come from?
一体どこから来たのでしょう
The answer lies in space.
答えは宇宙にあります
In massive stars that are 8 to 25 times heavier than our Sun.
太陽の8倍から25倍もの重さを持つ巨大な星
Their cores are worlds of unimaginably high temperature and pressure.
その難易度は想像を絶する高温高圧の世界です
Temperatures reach billions of degrees, and pressure is hundreds of billions of times Earth's atmospheric pressure.
温度は数十億度 圧力は地球の大気圧の数千億倍以上
In this extreme environment, which is extremely rich in neutrons compared to normal conditions, iron-58 captures neutrons to create iron-60.
この通常と比べて中性子が非常に多い極限環境で 鉄58が中性子を捕まえて鉄60が作られます
It's like cosmic alchemy.
まるで宇宙の錬金術ですね
And when a star reaches the end of its life, it creates one of the universe's most powerful explosions - a supernova.
そして星が一生を終えるとき超新星爆発という宇宙最大級の爆発を起こします
Its power is so great that it releases in just a few seconds the energy the Sun would emit over 10 billion years.
その威力は太陽が100億年かけて放出するエネルギーをたった数秒で放出するほど
This explosion scatters iron-60 throughout space.
この爆発で鉄60は宇宙空間にばらまかれるんです
From the 1960s to 1970s, the American research vessel Eltanin collected sediments - basically sand and rock fragments -
1960年代から70年代、アメリカの調査船エルタニン号が世界中の海底から堆積物、ありていに言えば砂や岩のかけらですね
from ocean floors around the world.
それを採取していました
This survey also provided important evidence for proving the theory of continental drift.
この調査は大陸移動説を証明するための重要な証拠にもなったそうです
But there was an astonishing discovery.
ところが驚くべき発見がありました
Iron-60, which shouldn't exist on Earth, was found in deep ocean floors across the Indian Ocean, Pacific Ocean, and Atlantic Ocean - all over the world.
インド洋、太平洋、大西洋、世界中の深海から地球には存在しないはずの鉄60が見つかったんです
Iron-60 that shouldn't be naturally produced on Earth.
地球では自然には作られないはずの鉄60
When and where did it come from?
一体いつ、どこからやってきたんでしょうか
When scientists examined the iron-60 in rock fragments collected from the ocean floor by Eltanin,
エルタニン号が海底から採取した岩のかけらの鉄60を調べたところ
interestingly, there were clear peaks in the amount of iron-60.
面白いことに鉄60の量には明確なピークがありました
About 1.7 to 3.2 million years ago,
約170万から320万年前と
and about 6.5 to 8.7 million years ago - two distinct periods.
約650万から870万年前の2つの時期
Apparently something special happened during these times.
どうやらこの時期に何か特別なことが起きていたようです
Scientists believe this is evidence of supernova explosions that occurred near Earth.
科学者たちはこれは地球の近くで起きた超新星爆発の証拠だと考えました
But "near" is relative on a cosmic scale.
でも近くといっても宇宙スケールでの話
The estimated distance is about 230 to 330 light-years away.
推定では約230から330光年離れた場所
A distance that would take over 200 years even at the speed of light.
光の速さでも200年以上かかる距離です
The iron-60 released by the supernova explosion
超新星爆発で放出された鉄60は
traveled through space for a long time,
長い時間宇宙空間を旅した後に
eventually entering Earth's atmosphere,
やがて地球の大気圏に突入
then raining down into the ocean,
そして海に降り注ぎ
and slowly accumulating on the ocean floor.
ゆっくりと海底に積もっていったんです
The fact that iron-60 continued to fall for 1.5 million years
150万年間も鉄六重が降り続いたということは
suggests not a single explosion,
1回の爆発ではなく
but likely multiple supernova explosions occurring in succession.
複数の超新星爆発が連続して起きた可能性が高いんです
Actually, our solar system is currently
実は私たちの太陽系は今
in what's called the Local Bubble,
局所泡と呼ばれる
a region of space particularly sparse in matter,
宇宙の中でも特に物質が少ない
like being inside a bubble.
まるで泡の中のような領域にいます
Its radius is about 500 light-years,
その大きさは半径約500光年
and it continues to expand at about 6.5 km per second even now.
現在でも秒速約6.5kmで広がり続けています
To explain this simply,
これをわかりやすく例えると
it's like blowing sand with a fan.
扇風機で砂を吹いた時のようなものなんです
The wind blows the sand away, leaving the center sparse,
風で砂が吹き飛ばされて中心部分はスカスカになり
while creating walls of sand around it.
周りに砂の壁ができますよね
Scientists believe this Local Bubble was created by
科学者たちはこの局所泡が過去1400万年の間に起きた
multiple supernova explosions over the past 14 million years.
複数の超新星爆発によって作られたと考えています
And the iron-60 in the deep ocean is an important clue to its formation process.
そして深海の鉄60はその形成過程の重要な手がかりなんです
But I'm sure many of you are wondering:
でも疑問に思った方も多いんじゃないでしょうか
How did they measure a substance with a half-life of 2.6 million years?
260万年も半減期がある物質をどうやって測定したんでしょう
Usually, the half-life of radioactive materials is measured by observing their decay.
通常放射性物質の半減期はその崩壊を観測して測ります
But 2.6 million years is longer than human history.
でも260万年なんて人類の歴史より長い
Observation would be impossible, right?
観測なんて無理ですよね
So scientists came up with a clever method.
そこで科学者たちは賢い方法を思いつきました
They artificially created iron-60 by bombarding copper with protons in a nuclear reaction,
同にプロトンを照射する核反応で人工的に鉄六重を生成し
then compared that iron-60 with iron-55, which has a half-life of 2.7 years.
その鉄60と半減期2.7年の鉄55と比較する方法です
Some of you may know about carbon-14 dating.
炭素14年代測定法を知っている方もいるかもしれません
That famous method used in archaeology to determine ages.
考古学で年代特定に使われるあの有名な方法です
Carbon-14 dating uses not only the radioactive isotope carbon-14,
炭素14年代測定法では放射性同位体である炭素14だけでなく
but also its ratio to the stable isotope carbon-12.
安定同位体である炭素12との比率を利用します
Rather than just measuring the absolute amount of carbon-14,
炭素14の絶対量を測定するだけでは除去しきれない
by comparing it with carbon-12, we can eliminate the effects
化石燃料や核実験などの外的要因による
of increased atmospheric carbon from external factors like fossil fuels and nuclear testing.
大気中の炭素の増加の効果を炭素12との比較によって取り除けるんですよね
Using a similar principle, by comparing with a substance of known half-life,
それと似た原理で既知の半減期を持つ物質と比較することで
we can accurately measure even long half-lives.
長い半減期も正確に測定できるんです
When we think of space research,
宇宙の研究といえば
most people imagine observing the universe with telescopes.
望遠鏡で宇宙を観測するようなことを想像する人が多いと思います
But the fact that treasures for unraveling cosmic mysteries
でも海の底深くに宇宙の謎を解き明かす宝物が
were sleeping deep in the ocean floor as radioactive isotopes
放射性同位体として眠っていた
is unexpectedly fascinating, don't you think?
ってのは意外性があってめちゃくちゃ面白くありませんか
Radioactive isotopes can act as clocks for recording the history of the universe and humanity.
放射性同位体って宇宙や人類の歴史を刻むための時計として活躍することもあるんですね
The connection between space, the ocean, and radiation, and how they became keys to solving cosmic mysteries - it's a wonderful example of how collaboration between different fields of knowledge leads to new discoveries.
宇宙と海、そして放射線が実はつながっていて、宇宙の謎を解き明かす鍵になった、そんな様々な分野の知見のコラボが、新しい発見につながった素晴らしい例だと思います。
The slides linked in the description delve into more technical content not covered in the video, so please check those out if you're interested.
概要欄にリンクを記載しているスライドでは、動画では触れていない、より専門的な内容に踏み込んでいるので、興味のある方はぜひそちらもご覧ください。
See you in the next video. Take care!
それではまた次回の動画でお会いしましょう ごきげんよう